Finding Aid for the Joseph L. Wyatt Collection of California Democratic Council Records, 1953-1967
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Joseph L. Wyatt Collection of California Democratic Council Records,
1953-1967
1082
Wyatt, Joseph L., 1924-
14 boxes (7 linear ft.)
The California Democratic Council (CDC), a federation of local volunteer clubs, was established in 1953. CDC endorsements and campaign support led to the first full statewide slate of Democrats in 40 years (1954) and also figured prominently in the election of Edmund G. Pat Brown as California governor in 1958. Joseph Lucian Wyatt, Jr. (b.1924) was the secretary of the California Democratic Council (1953-57), and president (1957-61). He was also the California delegate at the Democratic National Conventions in 1956, 1960, 1964, and 1968. The collection consists of correspondence, clippings, and printed material related to the formation, development, and activities of the California Democratic Council (CDC) between 1953 and 1967, and materials related to another organization, the Dime-A-Day Democracy Group.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph L. Wyatt, Jr., 1969.
Biography
Joseph Lucian Wyatt, Jr. was born in Chicago, Illinois, February 21, 1924; attended Northwestern University (AB, 1947) and Harvard Law School (LL.B., 1949); became a lawyer and sole practitioner, Los Angeles, California, in 1949; member California State Personnel Board, 1961-71; Director, Los Angeles Junior Chamber of Commerce, 1956-59; secretary, California Democratic Council (CDC), 1953-57; president, CDC, 1957-61; California delegate, Democratic National Convention, 1956, 1960, 1964, and 1968.
The California Democratic Council (CDC), a federation of local volunteer clubs, was established in 1953; under the direction of founding president Alan Cranston, the CDC was able to balance its electoral and legislative goals; CDC endorsements and campaign support led to the first full statewide slate of Democrats in 40 years (1954) and also figured prominently in the election of Edmund G. Pat Brown as California governor in 1958; as the CDC's focus became increasingly ideological, tensions led to a steady decline in its membership and presence in California politics; membership peaked at 75,000 in 1964.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, clippings, and printed material related to the formation, development, and activities of the California Democratic Council (CDC) between 1953 and 1967. Materials relate to Wyatt's involvement in the CDC as its secretary and president. Also contains materials related to another organization, the Dime-A-Day Democracy Group.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Wyatt, Joseph L., 1924- --Archives.; California Democratic Council--Archives.; Democratic Party (Calif.).; California--Politics and government, 1951- .
Container List
- 1952-1955
  - Campaign literature, 1952 election. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes material on R. Nixon, John J. Sparkman, Adlai Stevenson, Dean E. McHenry, et al.
  - CDC - Convention notes, Fresno., November 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dime-A-Day for Democracy., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CDC - Convention notes, Fresno., February 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dime-A-Day for Democracy., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous conventions constitutions., 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes CDC, Congressional, and assembly districts.
  - Pre-primary campaign literature., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes material on Goodwin Knight, Pat Brown, Stevenson, Steve Zetterberg, Edward R. Roybal, Richard Graves, Jesse Unruh, Samuel Yorty, Laurance Cross, et al.
  - Campaigns. George L. Thomas for Council., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1955-1956
  - CDC Convention., March 19-20, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CDC Convention, continued. Correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CDC Convention - Minutes., 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dime-A-Day for Democracy., 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - CDC Correspondence - Complaint letters., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - CDC Minutes., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Primary campaign literature., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Democratic National Convention., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General campaign., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes literature on Yorty, Nixon, Stevenson, Thomas Kuchel, Richard Richards, et al. (clippings, campaign literature, some correspondence).
- 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - CDC Convention., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CDC Legislative letter., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - CDC Lists., 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - CDC Minutes., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - CDC Correspondence., 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 2, 6-9)
    - 1957. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1958 July-September. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1958 October-November. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1958 December. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Congratulatory., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - CDR, Minutes., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 1958-1959
  - CDC - Mosk for Attorney-General., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - CDC - Right-to-work legislation., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - CDC - Pre-primary registration data., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - CDC Committees., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - CDC Convention., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - CDC Correspondence., 1959 (Box 4-5)
    - 1959 January. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1959 February. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1959 March. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1959 April. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1959 May. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1959 June. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1959 July. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1959 August. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1959 September. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1959 October. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1959 November-December. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CDC - Eagle (Clair)., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - CDC - Engle for Senate., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - CDC Issues conference., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
- 1959-1960
  - CDC Legislative., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - CDC Legislative letter., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - CDC Legislative letter., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Correspondence.
  - CDC Lists., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - CDC Minutes., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - CDC Newsletter., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - CDC - Out-of-state correspondence., 1959-61 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - CDC Research re Nixon., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - CDC Convention., 1960 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - CDC correspondence., 1960 (Box 7, Folder 1-12)
    - 1960 January. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1960 February. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1960 March. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1960 April. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1960 May. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1960 June. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1960 July. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1960 August. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1960 September. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1960 October. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1960 November. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 1960 December. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - CDC Issues conference., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    i.e. correspondence, etc. re conference.
  - CDC Issues conference., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - CDC - Kennedy for President., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - CDC Legislative letter., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - CDC Lists., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - CDC Minutes., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - CDC Presidential delegation (prior to 1960 convention). (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - CDC Primary campaign., 1960 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - CDC Publicity., 1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - CDC Publicity, clippings., 1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Democratic National Convention, General., 1960 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Democratic National Convention, California Democratic delegation., 1960 (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
- 1961-1963
  - CDC Board of Directors., April 1961 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - CDC Convention., 1961 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - CDC Correspondence., 1961 January-March (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - CDC Issues conference. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - CDC Legislative letter (Los Angeles)., 1961 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - CDC Legislative letter (San Francisco)., 1961 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - CDC Publicity., 1961 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Mostly clippings, many re Wyatt's retirement as president of CDC.
  - CDC Convention, Fresno., January 26-28, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Elections., 1962 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - CDC Convention., 1963 (Box 10, Folder 9a)
  - Kennedy assassination, clippings., 1963 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- CDC Convention, Rules committee., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - CDC - Cranston for U.S. Senate., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - CDC Legislative newsletter., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - CDC Lists. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - CDC Primary., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Mostly Cranston for Senate.
  - CDC Publicity, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Includes Governor Brown press releases.
  - Democratic National Convention, California delegation., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- 1965-1966
  - CDC Convention., 1965 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - CDC Convention, photographs., 1965 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Johnson Inauguration, memorabilia., 1965 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous., 1965 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Brown campaign., 1966 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Includes other campaign literature - e.g. Lloyd Hand for lieutenant governor Cranston.
  - CDC Convention., 1966 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Campaign Literature., 1966 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Politics, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Mostly re Brown campaign.
- 1966-1967
  - Election - Proposition #1, (re public retirement funds)., 1966 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - CDC Convention., 1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- CDC Miscellaneous Files, 1966-1967
  - Brown, Edmund G. (Pat)., 1958-1965 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - CDC - Descriptive literature for distribution. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - CDC - Clyde Doyle. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - CDC - Election reform reapportionment. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - CDC - Pre-primary endorsements. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Including draft (carbon) of Preprimary Endorsement by Leonard Rowe, September 1960.
  - CDC Publicity., 1958-59 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - CDC Publicity - Retraction statements., 1960 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    Includes anti campaign material put out in 1960 election campaign.
  - CDC - Report of President Joseph L. Wyatt., 1958 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Includes a carbon typescript of Cranston's speech at founding of CDC, 1953.
  - CDC Resolutions., 1958-1962 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Includes material on Nixon's governor's race.
  - Diogenes club. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets., v.d. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Mostly re California Democratic politics, 1952-66.
Partial List of Correspondents in Collection
Anderson, Glenn M. lieutenant-governor of California
Bowlest Chester
Brown, Edmund G. (Pat) governor of California
Burns, Hugh California State Senate
Cranston Alan
Doyle, Clyde California congressman
Eagle, Clair California senator
Galbraith, John Kenneth
Gore Albert Tennessee senator
Hanna, Richard T. California state legislator
Johnson, Lyndon Baines Senate majority leader
Kefauver, Estes Senator
Miller, George California congressman
Mosk, Stanley judge and California state attorney-general
Pitchess, Peter J. Los Angeles County sherrif
Rees, Thomas California state legislator
Richards, Richard California state legislator
Roosevelt, James California congressman
Schleisenger, Arthur M. Jr.
Unruh, Jesse California state legislator
Wagner, Robert F. Jr. New York City mayor
Wyman, Rosalind Los Angeles City councilwoman
Yarborough, Ralph Texas senator
Yorty, Samuel Los Angeles Mayor
Ziffren, Paul Democratic national committeeman
Related Material
CDC Officer: 1953-1965 [oral history transcript] / Wyatt, Joseph L., interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1971. Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
California Democratic Council Records (Collection 1389). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.